welcome everyone to our monthly Q&A
sorry that we had to miss last month but
in some ways the world ended so you guys
know what what was happening but we're
reconfiguring the world right now and so
I'm in a different place but we're gonna
do the Q&A nevertheless so let's start
we'll work our way down and see we have
a bit of time to take questions from
people that are online chat so the first
question is from Clinton who's a patron
so thank you for your support Clinton
it's another long question so I'll try
and read it very carefully at the lean a
little bit there because the way the
screens are guys so it's all improvised
and adduct okay could you address more
the bad trip aspects of the spiritual or
revelatory experience which might lead
to trauma paranoia
megalomania delusion I am worrying it us
into the sort of discussion you have
that there is somewhat of a row extent
of the experience of engagement in
dialog with deeper truths can an
authentic experience of the sort lack
confrontation with the ills and evils of
the world
and immense sorrow fear disgust
mortality and temptation towards power
so that's an excellent question Clinton
I would point you to one of the first
talks I gave I think is the very thought
that gave I think it was a I think was a
mindmatters talk on altered states of
consciousness and one of the things I
was trying to argue and I do argue is
that because these states put us in a
situation in which our salience
landscape is being transformed and being
altered they do make us tremendously
liable vulnerable to bullshitting to
self-deception and so I've always argued
I will continue to argue that it is I
think wrong both epistemic Lee and
morally to pursue these higher states of
consciousness these kinds of what you
termed revelatory experiences in a
fashion that's in the
handed from the cultivation of wisdom I
think that's a deep mistake
I think we have to independently
cultivate skills and virtues for seeing
through self-deception through the ways
in which we ourselves and for
tracking with good reason and evidence
the real patterns in the world and that
that has to be integrated with the
cultivation of higher states of
consciousness transformative experiences
I think the artistry by which we're
reformulating our sensibility in these
higher cognitive state higher states of
higher consciousness always needs to be
wedded to the the you know the
argumentation and reflection and virtue
the discernment of the sage and so I
think I'm going to take this as an
opportunity of saying that I challenge
the I think romantic interpretation of
these states or the use of substances
that engender these states in which the
point is just to have an extraordinary
experience that somehow expresses our
true self as I've said repeatedly I
think the attempt to demonize or deify
any of our faculties or aspects of our
psyche is a deep mistake and that we are
very prone to self-deception in such
higher states of consciousness but that
doesn't mean that they're not valuable
the higher states of consciousness have
optimized in many ways compositionally a
perspective only in participatory but
nevertheless we need to bring in
imported skills and virtues of
rationality not just propositional
rationality procedural perspective and
participatory rationality to ameliorate
the threat of self-deception that is
attended upon these states and also to
resist the temptation to demonize or
deify any aspect of the psyche now on
the depths of the psyche that we might
encounter and also to continually keep
that exploration of the depths of the
psyche wedded to the very careful
pursuit of
hang up on the real patterns in the
world so the next is from the patron
Connor how would you compare and
contrast belief versus making something
viable for oneself related to escaping
existential inertia and self-deception
so that's actually good so existential
inertia is when we're trapped within a
particular worldview and we we don't
know how to get out of it very often
people go into therapy because and this
is where the answer to Connors question
can begin because they often have the
correct beliefs they might believe that
they might believe that they're being
too avoided they have a proposition that
even might be well evidenced justify
that they assent to but it is inadequate
for them being able to become the kind
of person they want to be that's why
they go into therapy people very rarely
go into therapy without some beliefs
Ettrick says that something is wrong
they can usually state what is wrong but
stating what is wrong is very different
from knowing how to aspire how to engage
in transformation how to reconfigure
your salience landscape how do we
configure the agent arena relationship
how to find out how to find different
ways of being right that will afford you
getting out of the place where you're
locked or stuff that's what I mean about
making something viable for something to
be viable is precisely when you get a
stacking as my friend Jordan Hall says
of the four kinds of knowing when the
propositional knowing is afforded by and
in concert with your skills being
powerful and those skills are afforded
by are afforded by you in concert with
your perspective of knowing giving you
good reliable situational awareness
which is concert with your participatory
knowing which is ways adopting
existential modes forms of life as
vicarage might say that properly Co
shaped you in the environment and you
know whether these are work
and you know what it's not working like
when you go to another culture or where
you're in solitary confinement and
things become unglued in that fashion
so viability for me means that you're
getting a stacking of the four kinds of
knowing such that you're getting all of
the ways you're getting all of the
normative feedback that you're connected
to reality you're getting conviction of
the truth of your beliefs but also a
more importantly you're getting an
empowerment of your skills you're
getting a you're getting a sense of
presence yeah in your situational
awareness and you're getting a sense of
the emergence of affordances that you
and the environment belong together in a
primordial fashion so that's how I would
answer that question I hope that was
helpful
Conor mackenzie levitt patron i always
like a first from Mackenzie I hope
you're doing well Mackenzie what role do
you see your deal logos discussion is
playing in the current meeting Kairos
with a salons so that's a really good
question
and what I'm trying to do is afford a
way of accessing and activating and
accelerating collective intelligence so
that it self-organized this what
bootstraps up into collective
rationality and collective wisdom so
that the cultivation of individual
wisdom and collective wisdom are in
concert and mutually affording
reciprocally opening each other up and I
think that is very important because
it's only in at the level of collective
wisdom that we will appropriately learn
how to relate to our intelligibility
regain our intimacy with intelligibility
our meaning making and also get the
wisdom to properly select vet coordinate
ecologies of practices that are going to
be needed to reconfigure our ways of
being on ways of seeing in our ways
appear so I think the DIA logos
especially when it's doing both of these
because that's what
the meta secret technology music Jordan
halls term ancient dialectic did it
coordinated the individual motivation of
wisdom and the collective cultivation of
wisdom in a reciprocally
open fashion and Eve people the serious
play the taste of alternative ways of
being this is this is the place in with
India logos where we had collate the the
individual and collective wisdom like I
say in reciprocal opening that also
gives us a taste of a different way of
being a way of being that might help to
reformulate our culture in general and I
as I'd like to point out you know this
is not some utopian fantasy Socrates was
doing this in Athens while it was under
siege for an extended period of time and
in which you know people are there's
there's there had been a plague a
literal plague and that had killed many
of the Athenians and even Pericles the
leader so Socrates was in a situation
very much like ours and he was
practicing I don't want to be
pretentious here I'm trying to emulate
practicing something that bridges
between what he was doing and all the
emerging biological practices I see like
I said stop circling etc bridge between
them so that we can do what he did he
helped create taste for new ways of
being and afford the cultivation of
wisdom within those new ways of being
that permeated out through Greek culture
and through Roman culture and laid in
important ways the foundation for an
axial way of being that you know then
went into Christianity etc was it
perfect was it flawless no but did it
did it enliven enrich and expand the
field of human experience in a profound
way that was needed with the changes
that were happening in the world I would
argue that it did so I think that that
is what I'm aspiring of course with the
help of many brilliant and talented
people like Jordan Paul guy says thought
Peter Lindbergh I
I'm Christopher master Pietro my beloved
friend so another question from surgery
who's also a patron the question about
meditation that concerns me for a long
time is how do I know that I'm doing it
right where rather than deluding myself
it seems that if I'm doing it wrong it
probably will just improve my skill of
self-delusion that rather than presence
of mindfulness so this is an important
question
one thing I would ask if every this
question comes up a lot and so I'm not
trying to pick on surrogate I would ask
people that asks this question that they
when they men need to do is ask this
question existentially like right so you
right how do you know that you're in
relationship with being in your everyday
life how do you know that you're in
right relationship with yourself in your
everyday life and so I think you should
fit all you should have a comprehensive
and integrated questioning and that's
part of my answer there is nothing
really in the meditation per se that
will tell you if you're doing it right I
can give you phenomenological tips these
are this is the language of training to
help you get to a place but that's
different from what you're asking you're
asking for yes but you know what
justifies this being the right way so I
use the example often that in meditating
you're stepping back and looking at your
mind rather than automatically looking
through it but happen because you might
notice distortions in on the lenses
distortion distorting patterns right of
processing in your mind but how do you
know that that was a distortion there's
something on the lens but how do you
know well this is what you have to do
you also have to practice putting on
your glasses and looking out and seeing
if you see things new the meditation is
working if not you're getting you know
insight so much in the meditation but if
you're starting to have moments of
connectedness realization insight in
your life that track that solve problems
right that reduce conflict that afford a
sense of connectedness to yourself and
others but more important than your
judgment about whether or not right your
behavior is changing is the judgment of
other people
and in don't go seeking it with if
people come to you and say because this
is what this is what I've noticed and
other people are reported if people come
to you and say hey what's different
about you you're you're a little bit
more flexible you're a little bit more
balanced you a little bit a little bit
more equanimity you feel a little bit
more centered that's how you know and
you also do the reverse when you're out
in the world and you're really connected
or you're really in a state of flow or
you've had a genuine insight that's
solved a real problem
what does that feel like what does that
feel like and use that as a touchstone
when you're within your meditation what
does that feel look so you're trying to
create this loop this self-correcting
loop between right is what's happening
in my meditation and my contemplation
transforming my action in the world in a
way that can be called realization and
are other people noticing that and do
those realizations reliably feedback
into my meditation and help me hone in
on what I'm trying to achieve in the
practice that's the loop by which you
decide if you're doing it correctly so
well I'm doing this because I'm not
saying I'm not putting it in quotations
what I'm doing is saying that you have
to sort of take that provisionally
because this is your it's going to get
better it's like when you're trying to
do and martial art when you're trying to
learn a move the Tai Chi classics talked
about drawing a circle with your free
hand you draw it really properly right
and then you look at real circles and
you go back and forth but then you start
to also feel from the inside oh I can
sort of feel the difference between
drawing a good circle and a bad circle
and then oh and now I notice things
about real circles that I wasn't
noticing before and you do it until you
could draw right a good circle freehand
okay so that's what I meant it's it's
you're doing it correctly but that
correctly is always a self-correcting
process within that loop okay so
Victoria and she's a former university
youth he stood
it's it's nice to be in this even if
it's only virtual and somewhat displaced
communication with you again Victoria I
hope you're doing well I hope your child
is doing well is one of the rules of
meditative questing especially Who am I
the dissolution of fixed identity if so
could you please elaborate on that yes
it's I would put it more than its its
yeah that language is maybe a little bit
stronger than I would like I would say
it's more like loosening up the process
of Co identification the process by
which I'm us assuming an identity and
assigning identities and what I want is
I don't want that to be happening
unconsciously mindlessly and reactively
I want to be able to bring some
awareness in in it because if I bring
awareness then there's the possibility
of discernment there's the possibility
of remembering not just in thought but
in being sati remembering I am more and
other than this identity I've assumed
and in a resonant fashion that person is
more and other than the identity I've
assigned and perhaps if I engage in the
reciprocal opening I can come to relate
to that person not a cavern mode but in
the bien mode and / and perhaps not just
that person but to Asia or the world and
and perhaps right if I can more reliably
remember to be in the being mode in
relating to things that I can afford
with the being mode of force I can
afford development and I can then see my
identity as something that's
aspirational that I'm developing rather
than something that I have or possess or
merely control this is very much
Socrates's
proposal to us Christopher Moore in his
book on Socrates and self-knowledge it
like makes the argument that Socrates
was offering the model of the
aspirational self in place of you know
that sort of common sense or romantic
sense of the self as what we have within
us that's constant and static and sort
of unchanging
so the next question is from Dan patron
excellent some of the conversations I
have with them are sort of mind
expanding I really admire the
flexibility the scope and the dynoed the
dynamic quality of dance thinking his
question is what role if any do you
think that hubris and nemesis are
playing in the present unfolding of the
meta-crisis I think it's important first
of all to bring that up and I want to
first and this came up in a really
excellent discussion if it was good back
and forth between Reed Kelly and I on
this about you know that we tended to
take we tended to do a couple thing so
Zack Stein is making a very good
argument that in in the crisis that
we're in and Jordan Hollis has talked
about this and so if I we-we're tend to
fallen back on mythopoetic ways of
thinking what we followed by the
mythopoetic because mythopoetic thought
is imaginal it's symbolic its gestural
it's a way of trying to stop all of the
kinds of knowing so it has this great
vertical integration mythopoetic
patterns are also ones that have
survived across the most cultural
context their perennial patterns in that
way and so they're look they're the most
likely to be transferable to our current
context so they have great vertical and
horizontal integration but that doesn't
mean the myth of poetic stuff doesn't
come up with without danger I mean so a
lot of the mythopoetic stuff that's
coming up for people with the dacovia
crisis is kind of this weird you know
almost old testament you know biblical
you know deity it's it's ubiquitous
right threat and it's it right it's
invisible and it can strike us without
without notice and it causes us to all
mistrust each other and it's demanding
tremendous purity codes from us and this
can get us into a kind of thinking in
which conspiracy and scapegoating and
trying to you know deal with the impure
can't come to mind so the mythopoetic
stuff comes up and the meeting crisis
has left us into place where we're sadly
lacking in the you know in a religious
official education for how to properly
relate to the imaginal and make use of
it and so that there's that's an issue
and so this mythopoetic stuff can come
up and it can make be incredibly
inflationary for us it can give us a
sense of undue confidence that we know
what the right way to go is and so well
we we well we shouldn't try and shut off
the mythopoetic that's also the wrong
response because it's coming up
precisely because of its adoptive
functionality we have to bring a
reflective rationality to bear on it and
what does that mean that means that in
addition think about and this is you
know that goes back to the point I was
making with ray of Kelly our culture has
become really fascinated with the hero
and his rave Kelly pointed out I've
misunderstood this a bit because he
thinks the hero archetype you know
culture has been reduced to the warrior
and what we have is all of the yang of
the hero and none of the year none of
the receptivity and so first of all
there's that way in which we're warping
it and so and you can think about how
the warrior archetype is so in sync with
that kind of us versus them and the
purity code and conquest and control
right so there's that confusion and
secondly we've forgotten that yes the
Greeks gave us hero myths
you know Theseus and Odysseus but for
every hero myth they also give us a
hubris myth they give us Icarus and they
give us Phaeton and they give us a rack
net people who tried to conquer the
domain of the gods inflation and were
smashed because of them
and we got to remember the hubris side
of right of our mythological education
to counterbalance the temptations
towards inflation and a almost
militaristic response and I
worried about the the combination of
this biblical language a days of
judgment it this way of thinking right
and the fact that we're calling it
plague right and also this the
militaristic language of reign of war we
have to fight it at conquer and we have
to find out and the rise of all the
conspiratorial thinking so again we have
to be very very careful right with the
mythopoetic stuff that comes up and so
we have to re-educate ourselves in terms
of the that like the ecology of you know
the systemic relationship between myths
and how they try to get it give us a
virtual governor the hero myth right it
enables us it encourages us but the
hubris myths there are selective
constraint limiting us so that we don't
become inflationary we don't be we don't
give in to militaristic conspiratorial
purity code narratives so I think all of
this is tremendously important and the
fact that many of us write our sort of
religiously illiterate and also we're
illiterate because the way our culture
has functioned about dealing with the
this mythopoetic machinery that's a
worrying thing and so I'm worried that
what following what's going to follow on
the heels for example of the co-lead
crisis is a sort of an accelerated you
know mental health crisis the meeting
crisis is being exacerbated in many ways
by this so I think we need to be I think
there was an excellent question by Dan I
think we need to bring back the dynamic
self-organizing ecology of mythology of
entire systems of myth and use that in
discussion with our best reflected
philosophical best philosophical
reflection and scientific understanding
so that we craft a virtual engine in
which that that mythopoetic way of
thinking and being can come to an
adaptive expression
so another question from David sweat
Lowe a patron and I'm always grateful
for it for a lot of the commentary and
involvement that David has in my work
David's question is the following my
contemplative work centers on how
propositional trust differs from
participatory trust and moves from a
thesis of obeying external authority
through the antithesis of listening to
inner Authority towards a synthesis of
mutual authority between me and my arena
in participatory knowing this feels like
the god that is not a god but the
temptation to give in to grandiosity
becomes intense you have a similar
personal struggle as you strive to be of
service to this effective moment if you
talk about that wow that is fantastic
question and it's fantastic because
let's let's sort of work the way into it
so David is you know the God that's not
a god or the god that's beyond god this
is teller and Tillich importantly talked
about these three ways in which we
understand the authority with terms of
which we understand normativity Tillett
talked about heteronomous that's when we
feel like there's an external authority
imposing on us and then what we have
largely done from the Enlightenment
onward I mean like the historical period
is we have resisted arguments of
authority that normativity Authority
arguments at least we do that officially
and we have we have instead given our
allegiance to autonomy the the the so
what matters it is autonomy and virtues
like that like one understanding of
authenticity not the hi to Gary emotion
but a more prevalent common notion of
authenticity you know and so this is
autonomous and a completely
self-governing and this is this is
important and caught was caught late
sees three critiques you put a pure
reason practical reason cetera and the
point about this and this is Hubbard
Mouse's point he
is autonomy right it's an extent it's
part of that Cartesian subjectivity that
ultimately I'm the only authority on
myself and what's that done for us well
that has limited these because what
happens is that reason morality and
aesthetics truth goodness and beauty are
fragmented and separate they're
autonomous and uncoordinated
incommensurable with each other and this
is ultimately not viable and livable for
us truth goodness and beauty have two
mutually constrain effective
interpenetrate each other and some of
our some of our cutting-edge thinkers
are getting us back towards and so we
have to get past yet the you know the
heteronomous normativity gift that gives
all power to the objectivity and the
autonomous normativity that gives all
power to subjectivity what did until he
proposed well he proposed the Animus he
proposed that transductive one that
David is talking about that resonance
that unfolding and that is that was the
kind of faith that Tillich was talking
about that would get us into the guard
beyond all God now that beyond all
possible guards beyond the god of theism
what's going on there and this is the
caution and this links up with what I
previously said that Killick brings in
Tillich is reminding us that our
relationship is transductive and
participatory and that there is a
constant temptation to try and
appropriate it subjectivity or give it
over to some objectivity in a process
that he calls idolatry and idolatry is
exactly that idolatry is to have the
idea that what I want to do is I want to
foreclose on this I want to foreclose it
and I want to come to some state of
possession of the sacred and if you so
for in my practice what I regularly and
reliably do is I engaged practices that
are designed to foreground the
participation
for around the chunji activity and call
me to the fact that you know in Kelvin
said this you know human in our
imagination is a factory for the you
know the ongoing production of idols
we are constantly tempted to idolatry
and so I barely remind myself that I
make a vow it's kind of like between a
vow and a prayer in the sense of trying
to find myself and conform myself to the
ongoing you know I want to come into a
right relationship an ongoing right
relationship conformity with this
ongoing disclosure the reciprocal
opening and so I make a bow to myself
you know to to remember the temptation
to idolatry either subjective idolatry
of inflation or objective inflation of
the great leader that's also idolatry
and we've seen we're seeing both of
those right now just like Tigers let
loose all right and you know just to
remember like how important humility is
how important it is to be honest how
important it is to honor and help other
people to constantly look for
self-deception for a sense of
self-importance for self-centeredness
for self-righteousness and so I I engage
in daily practices there try to
foreground my salience landscape unto
the participatory relationship with
entrenched activity thing about it in
right relationship rather than as a
attempted foreclosure and Daly reminding
myself of the temptation towards
idolatry so that's that's how I'm gonna
that's the answer trying to give you
David ah so we have another question
from Karima
Cynthia Clayton and Kariba eyes also
partaking in the meditation course so I
want to answer her question
she's been somebody that sort of made
some wonderful comments on my video
series and like I said she's always
she's very diligent in meditation quest
so so thank you for that thank you for
your participation
rather long with I feel that this
pandemic is an evolutionary driver
global crisis is for change and offer
opportunity for a paradigm shift to tell
a new story of who we are and our goals
for Humanity in your recent talk with
Thomas Bjorkman yet Thomas Bjorn is the
he's the person from whom I learned this
idea of the meta-crisis you define the
future state as not physical but a state
of being of mental emotional mastery are
leading to personal enlightenment and
universal goodwill you spoke of the
notion of trust
daring to let go with a collective leap
of faith and opening a space for an
emerging collective imaginary please
define collective imaginary and other
aspects of the new reality we could help
to birth giving birth or that's that's
also a Socratic metaphor
Socrates compared himself to Midwife and
remember that the word concept
ultimately comes from the verb conceive
which ultimately means the ability to
give birth ultimately our deepest
conceptions should be giving birth to
new ways of being and in which
personhood and the community of
personhood is you know he is afforded
and improved so so I mistook I was
talking to Thomas and Jordan about this
and also with Chris and with Andrew C
Sweeney enzymes
Zachary Stein who's written some extra
excellent work on how we're in the this
we're in a critical period a period of
criticality where the system can really
organize itself and you know I'm calling
it a Kairos where you know normally you
know the course of events is like a
river to the sizes are sort of inertial
and then ability to it there's very
little we can do but what happens and
this is also a notion that till it
thought from Christianity that I got
from tiller when you get a Kairos you
get the fullness of time that that
course actually let's say it will play
with it roads or changes the bank of the
river there's like the course changes
the conditions and now there's Eddie's
and there's a chance right that the
system that the course of the river
could change and now actions that
normally would have been
just absorbed and overwhelmed by the
inertial flow actions this is called
sensitive dependence on initial
conditions actions now you can't become
very powerful in the sense that
previously what would have been a
smaller insignificant action can have
huge ramifications of time and I'm going
to use the distinction from Pascal
Pascal made a distinction between the
spirit of geometry and a spirit of
finesse the spirit of geometry is that's
how we have normally experienced time
it's you know it's like it's
mathematical it's calculated oh we can
project what that's going we can
calculate time is unfolding it's the
spirit of geometry but when you're in
Kairos you have to move to what Pascal
called the spirit of finesse now finesse
and notice how this makes sense with
respect to Kairos a finesse the spirit
of finesse is that combination of
procedural and perspective I will and
even participatory knowing that's the
right that's about timing and placing
because when you're in the car us the
timing and the placing of your actions
can have huge consequences and so you
need to have that cultivated sense of
finesse and so if you have that
cultivated sense of finesse that puts
you into a continuity of contact so that
you're in right relationship to the
course of events and you can write you
can with your actions you have that
discernment the right timing and the
right placement so think about the other
an example I sometimes use like if you
like when is the right moment to first
kiss someone and the spirit of geometry
won't work for you you've got to be in
the situation what Nora Bateson calls
the warm data you have to be immersed in
you have to have a procedural and
perspectival and participatory immersion
in the complexities of the dynamical
system that it's unfolding and you have
to reconfigure yourself
you have to become yourself an unfolding
dynamical system so you can define
yourself so you can get them into
resonance with that and so you know now
is the right moment and the timing and
the placement and if if you discern it
right if you are coupled to the course
of events in the right way and you kiss
her the right way at the right time the
course of events of your relationships
change and something comes a new way of
being comes in to being for the two of
you same thing that's what I'm trying to
get out with the sense of faith I'm
trying to get that sense that you're in
the spirit of finesse and you're getting
that resonant right resonant coupling to
the dynamical system you yourself are a
dynamical system in conformity with it
and you are getting a sense of timing
and placement so that you can maintain
that continuity you can be in right
relationship with it so you can follow
and participate and help their wrecked
the course and what I'm what we might be
able to direct it to you because in a
Kairos you always have opposite things
that are equally potentially available
right and that's what everything is in
the balance and we could go with we
could we could discern what the
opportunity for moving to a situation in
which the we have we get a normativity
other than the normativity of just
producing and consuming and busyness and
business that we have a we bring back
the normativity the important because
this is what we're discovering we're
discovering that a lot of the stuff that
was sowed in so many demands on us
actually falls away now I I'm not trying
to be dismissive of people who are sick
or are suffering economic
that's real if that has to be addressed
I'm talking about the people in which
what's coming to the fore is a lot of
the stuff that was consuming their time
in their identity has fallen away and
they need more resilience and deeper
resources of meaning can we move to a
culture of wisdom cultivation meaning
facilitation in which trying to create
communities in which personhood is the
thing that we most evaluate our self by
rather than you know wealth we've gotten
messed up in a lot of ways we've
confused wealth with subjective
well-being wealth
initially when wealth is initially very
powerful of increased subjective
well-being it gets you out of poverty
and you get subjective well-being that
sense of it's good I feel good but and
then it plateaus and it takes huge
differences wealth to make small
differences in subjective well-being so
we we shouldn't be using wealth is our
only metric of subjective well-being and
secondly we shouldn't be confusing
subjective well-being with meaning in
life they aren't identical they come
apart they come apart when you're
engaged in the entropic project of
having a child when you have a child
your subjective well-being collapses you
know everything about your subjective
well-being your health your sleep your
eating everything is challenged and
diminished why do people do it because
meaning and life goes up they feel
connected to the project of meaning
making that is person making we need to
reorient our culture so that meaning
making in person making have as much a
normative demand on us as the production
of wealth I'll say it once again I'm not
a Marxist I'm not saying that wealth is
evil I'm saying let's go back to being
rational about wealth let's really
understand its relationship to happiness
and then reconfigure our culture more
appropriately I am willing and I have
already enacted
I'm willing and I know a lot of people
are I'm willing to take a systemic
reduction in my standard of living we're
all doing it right now if I can trust
that I'm participating in a process that
is going to afford me more meaning so I
want you know I want to try and
cultivate in myself and how cultivate
and others that kind of faith not the
assertion of some utopic certainty or
some nostalgic certainty but that
finesse that continuity of contact that
puts me into right relationship with the
unfolding dynamics of the Kairos so that
I can help tip the balance towards
bringing back a way of being in which
wisdom and meaning are at least as
important culturally not individually
autodidactic Li but Colette culturally
to us as wealth is that's part of what I
see happening I know that Thomas argues
this Thomas has argued that what has
happened through the Enlightenment and
the postmodern critique is that we have
we you know the Enlightenment basically
undermine the normativity of God and
then the in might and then the
post-modernism sort of in undermine the
you know the the normativity of science
and reason but what happened is that the
market was left as the sole normativity
the sole God for us and that's a very
dangerous place to be we should always
have multiple sources of normativity
that can act as significant checks and
balances on us so that was a long answer
but I think that was a really important
question I tried to answer it as
comprehensively as I can here's a
question from Rob who's also a patron is
the world doing good problem formulation
on the scene dacovia epidemic or in what
way could we be framing this better it's
hard to answer about the world because
there's significant differences between
different countries you know I'm a
Canadian and I see there's very
differences significant differences
between Health Canada has been handling
this and for example how the United
States has been handling
and you know that's not just my opinion
I've been communication lots of
Americans and there's sort of you know
yet saying together there are
significant differences and I think
that's so answering about the world as a
whole is difficult one thing I would say
about that is I think the problem
formulation needs to be more expansive
and I I've tried to indicate how we're
still locked into right the political
market arena as our only normativity our
only way of evaluating this and even if
we take the notion of health right the
notion of health should not just be
biological health or economic health the
notion of health has to be also
existential health and mental health and
I see III think that already existential
and mental health issues and if you'll
allow me spiritual issues that weave
them together these are already taking a
significant toll on people
loneliness experience of Dhamma side
right like I said a sense of being
almost in a surreal existence lots of
people are using that adjective now
everything feels surreal
that's a canary in the coal in the coal
mine
pay attention to that that's important I
think you need to start broadening what
we mean by health because if I think
we're facing you know you know a mental
health / existential / spiritual crisis
of tsunami proportions and it's already
starting to unfold and we need to think
about what kind of interventions we need
to put in place to respond to that so I
want to thank the patreon subscribers
and everyone watching right now it's
always really great I love these
questions and answers and you know and
many of you you know simple questions we
have to put aside for maybe another time
I try to usually only answer one
question per patron because we're trying
to get as many questions answered as
possible your support the
patrons support of course is crucial to
continuing to produce these videos and
for supporting the science that I'm
engaging in and also the practical
instruction like my meditation course
that I'm offering online to help find
solutions and viable responses to the
vena crisis we're going to shift to some
live questions from the chat one is from
David Carr doe what is your take on this
state's myths we should abandon all
religion altogether and replace it with
the very useful field of philosophy um
so in what in one way I agree with that
and in another way I disagree with that
and so that sounds terrific ly Canadian
a so so so let me try I think a better
way of looking at it because that's kind
of a VAT economy that we inherited very
deeply from the Enlightenment and the
idea that all of tradition was something
that we had to reject and that was
important because like I said that was
getting out of that sort of heteronomous
notion of normativity and developing
autonomy and that's something that was
exemplified in the philosophical work of
people like Descartes and cawed but if
you go earlier the distinction between
philosophy and religion breaks down if
you look at the whole neo platonic
tradition or you look at somebody like
you know Socrates or honesty or Agustin
depending on the pronunciation you want
to use I think that we should broaden
the notion of rationality so that it
starts to overlap again with wisdom that
what is primarily important about
rationality is overcoming self-deception
not just the logical Manomet management
of argumentation and we should give up
the mud off the monologic understanding
the autonomous understanding of Reason
as something that I just do as a
monologue there's more evidence coming
out that reason is better understood in
terms of distributed cognition that's
something that it's done in dialogue
it's also we should understand that we
have multiple kinds of multiple ways of
knowing and
that being rational proposition Lee is
not the same as how what is rational
procedurally or perspect traveling or in
a participatory manner so you know
there's ways of self-deception in
participatory knowing we can get into
the reciprocal narrowing of addiction
whether the identity of the world and
the identities collapse and become
fixated into an automatic you know and
reactive and unconscious and limiting
way that's right that's part of Mark
Lewis's notion so how you deal with
addiction is not through argumentation
you have to afford people reciprocal
opening you have to get I thought you
overcome that self-deception soon as we
see that that what we've brought the
notion of rationality and we make a
dialogic that of course right we're
talking about wisdom and dialogue that's
very philosophical but we're also
invoking right as I said we're also
invoking those forms of communication
that bridge between the kinds of knowing
we're going to the mythopoetic is going
to come up imaginal the symbolic ways in
which the unconscious and the conscious
might talk to each other ways and look
at my gesture my gesture is a way of
bridging between perspectival and
participatory prospective tribal and
propositional knowing and we know that
it's doing something above and beyond
what I'm doing with my speech how do I
bring gestural in the imagination in
because it is doing some of the
important work in my information
processing so to be philosophical and
look and understand and reflect on that
and try and free it from self-deception
and improve its ability to connect it's
going to involve me with the gestural
with the imaginal with the existential
with the symbolic and that's also wrote
religious in an important sense I think
what we want is we need rightful Asif II
that's more capable of being religious
in this sense according to a kind of
Socratic faith the kind of faith that
was talking about earlier the faith of
finesse and and and we need a religion
that is much more philosophical that
remember
that what it's about is religio
connectedness overcoming foolishness
affording wisdom and making persons
within communities of persons so that's
how I would answer that question another
question from them all what's your
perspective on the inner struggle of
freedom and duty should one pursue their
personal desires it means to strive
loved ones um no um I I don't I'm not
quite sure I want to I think I get I get
a sense I don't think I'm always
referring to just somebody who's
viciously selfish I think he's talking
about you know some of the wisdom
archetypes the sage archetypes like
Jesus who basically who-who said you
know if you're not willing to abandon
your mother and your father you can't
follow me or I think of Siddhartha
Gautama who you know who abandons his
wife and child in order to become fukuda
and this you know and then you get into
the dangerous territory and I'm always
uncomfortable you know when you move
into trip regards the teleological
suspension of the ethical so I don't
think first of all I don't think you
should pursue personal desires at the
expense of others I don't know how you
would justify that and I think that's
again to be trapped within autonomous
subjectivity of the way that fragments
us and undermines meaning meaning is
transgender
it's not subjective it's not objective
and so learning how to live transitive
ly is going to be the best way to afford
meaning and also cognition embodiment
and embeddedness and distributed
cognition are not separable from each
other they interpenetrate so I I can't
see any justification for its sort of
trying to abstract your personal desires
from that dynamic matrix first of all
and then giving some sort of special
privileged priority to it also does it
seek to be anything that I could justify
so I got I've got to say that I've got
to say that that's probably not the
intent of the question the question is
what do you do when you see
like Jesus or Suharto and the way I try
to understand that is in term and the
way I tried not just fall into the
dangers I feet I see a tendon on
kirkegaard notion of the teleological
suspension of the ethical that somehow
there's a higher purpose that we have to
we have to really limit it and constrain
it and I think that in moments of Kairos
some of the deepest patterns that we
have of connecting to other people are
in play right and what's going to happen
is those people are saying that their
affinity and their connection to the
logos of the Kairos of how its unfolding
itself organizing and making a new way
of being possible needs to be given
priority at this time precisely because
we're in Kairos and there's a there's an
important way in which the field of
human experience and being can be
fundamentally expanded and enriched for
many many people and so when it is clear
that that's the case then what should do
that and so I think what that means is
the only time in which you're allowed to
make that kind of sacrifice is when you
you're in clear Kairos and you have the
kind of overwhelming calling by that
Kairos and that is going to afford you
becoming well the Messiah or the Buddha
and since that's highly unlikely for
most of us I would say that that calling
better be really really powerful and it
better be leading to a progression that
is reliably being recognized by other
people as opening up a new way of being
that is the appropriate course of action
in the Kairos so that's how I would try
it put some very significant limitations
on trying to adopt the example of
Siddhartha
or Jesus of Nazareth Rollag on us
if introverts are adapted for social
condition situations what are introverts
adapted for us so I think introverts are
adopted we have you know these two these
two draws till it talks about the be
right in individuation and it overlaps
with Jung's notion and participation and
what is it we're most trying to do in an
event individuation it's not you know
the romantic notion of you know
realizing our true self that was always
there or collecting our autobiographical
specialness the idea is a
complexification that reduces inner
conflict and affords optimal
functionality and therefore is in
service of the other drive to drive to
participate the drive to be connected to
reality but the drive to connect to
reality should be internal izybelle
and give and afford us that better at
complexification getting the emergent
functions that reduce into conflict
so if extroverts are great at
participation introverts are directed
towards the the add activity of trying
to realize inner peace of course what we
want is an optimal relationship between
them which is why probably in
evolutionary terms we tend to get a
distribution of our population between
introverts and extroverts so that we
have lived reminders of the importance
of the connectedness to the world and to
each other's and lived reminder of the
importance of the connectedness we have
to ourselves and inner peace so this is
a question from Nicholas intagram from
Twitter is it possible to turn it out
into a net by expecting now to be a
thing that transforms you if so how can
you tell if you'd lead us so this goes
directly towards the heart of what I was
saying earlier you turn a vow into an it
when you make it an idol as opposed to a
symbol when you start looking at it and
trying to figure out why
ways in which I could manipulate it and
control it right on it and trying to
figure out what are the ways in which I
could manipulate it and control it right
so that I can come into full possession
of instead if you can right and that's a
having mode and it locks it down instead
you have to always relate to something
to relate to something as a now as a Tao
and I think this is one of the deep
insights of Neoplatonic Christianity
Eastern Orthodox Christianity to relate
to something to an app as a dhow and
what's the name of the guy who wrote God
you won't be in oh I can't remember his
name right now anyways that's a book
that talks about this at great length
the distinction between the icon and the
idol in the in the idol you you you you
you you sort of completely consumed
something with your gaze and you
completely appropriate it in the icon
you're always looking through it you're
relating to it in a being mode and
you're trying to open yourself up to it
so it can open itself up more sorry for
seizing itself language really right so
that it can bow yourself it more so the
inexhaustible nosov the Val can shine
through more and more this is how you
relate to your beloved or how you relate
to a work of art or how you relate to a
beautiful environment so I would say
take a look at are you in a relationship
where you're looking at an idol or are
you looking through an icon because if
you're looking through an icon because
you want you're acknowledging that it
will always withdraw beyond your grasp
and when you the more you acknowledge
that the more you let the inexhaustible
this of it shine through to you and
that's the way how you can is
allow and this is where we could this is
where we can get confused right that the
valleys shines but it's not that it's
not that it's not just a shine of
salience it's it's it's it's the shine
that is simultaneously giving us insight
and new intelligibility but also telling
us right giving us that the bit right
the the the the the remembering you know
of hubris and the reminder of inflation
it's all that they're just shining
that's also telling us that it's always
it exhaustively beyond us so the people
that I love the most that's one of the
things I'm trying to do in my Mehta
practice that I teach me it's a way of
reminding not in your thoughts but in
your being in your existential mode it's
a way of reminding yourself to get into
the being mode of people and relating to
them as that something you have to
practice to practice and practice and
practice and I encourage you to keep
doing so in these very dangerous times
being lovers in a dangerous time is a
really noble thing hence the Bruce
Coburn song right if we could because
when we're in scarcity it's so easy to
become cognitively inflexible and go and
lock down into just the having mode
control and consumption and then modal
confusion is rife and trying to remember
to be lovers not just romantic lovers
but lovers in Plato's sense the lovers
of wisdom the lovers of being that's
really important remembering that
remembering that okay thank you so much
for joining me today for this Q&A now
we're doing these every third Friday of
the month
I hope this worked for you guys I hope
it worked
thank you so much for the supporters on
patreon if you know your support helps
me to keep doing this and I hope this
isn't pretentious but you know I hope
that my work is helping others and so
you're helping me help others and that's
very important
please if you get a chance suggest my
work on the meeting crisis can others
they can watch the videos perhaps you
might want to consider supporting that
work that work and the work I'm doing
like the the meditation course or the
voices with reveille khadiyah logos
things that I'm doing that would be very
helpful to me we're doing meditation
class every day sorry let me be very
careful but there's a meditation course
I'm teaching it live streaming we do it
weekdays at 9:30 est Monday is the other
day I teach an important principle we
get we do an exercise so you get a
spiritual understanding and then we sit
and then there's QA and then Tuesday
through Friday we meet we sit there's
review and a longer Q&A if you want to
join us you're very welcome to do so you
can go on any one of the videos and
you'll find a link to the previous sits
and the previous lessons so that you can
catch up and join us I would recommend
doing this by the way learning to you
know meditate and contemplate for
discernment and Socratic faith is really
really needed right now so I want to
finally thank my dear friend and techno
mage amar who has been here behind the
scenes as always making sure that
technology that godlet limps manages to
keep walking you know harmoniously
forward for us so that we were able to
do this all together so thank you very
much everybody
Thank You amar and I look forward to our
next session together in you know months
heart take care everyone